Thomas Lowe Hughes Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Thomas Lowe Hughes Papers 1918-2018 1961-1991
MSS86254
Hughes, Thomas Lowe, 1925-
71,500 items
200 containers plus 5 classified
82 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Public official, diplomat. Correspondence, writings, notes, professional files, and other papers of Thomas Lowe Hughes documenting his career as a close aide to Chester Bowles and Hubert Humphrey, his service in the Department of State as the director of the Bureau of Intelligence and Research (1963-1969), and his work as president of the Carnegie Endowment for International Peace (1971-1991).
Acquisition Information
The papers of Thomas Lowe Hughes were given to the Library of Congress by Hughes in 2018.
Transfers
Audiovisual materials have been transferred to the Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division where they are identified as part of the Thomas Lowe Hughes Papers. Among the transferred items are audio and video recordings of Hughes's speeches. Patrons are encouraged to contact the Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division in advance of a research visit.
Other Repositories
Other records relating to Hughes and the Hughes family can be found at the Minnesota Historical Society. Records relating to Hughes and the Student Federalists movement can be found at the New York Public Library.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Thomas Lowe Hughes are open to research. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting.
National Security Classified Information
Government regulations control the use of national security classified items in this collection. Manuscript Division staff can furnish information concerning access to and use of classified material.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1925, Dec. 11 Born, Mankato, Minn.
1944 1945 National president, Student Federalists
1947 B.A., Carleton College, Northfield, Minn.
1949 Rhodes scholar, University of Oxford, Oxford, England M.A., University of Oxford, Oxford, England
1951 1952 Professional staff, United States Senate Subcommittee on Labor and Labor-Management Relations
1952 J.D., Yale University, New Haven, Conn.
1952 1964 Lieutenant and major, United States Air Force
1955 Married Jean Hurlburt Reiman (died 1993)
1955 1958 Legislative counsel, United States Senator Hubert H. Humphrey
1959 1960 Administrative assistant, United States Congressman Chester Bowles
1961 1969 Deputy assistant secretary, deputy director, and director, Bureau of Intelligence and Research, Department of State
1965 Awarded Arthur S. Flemming award
1969 1970 Minister and deputy chief of mission, United States Embassy, London, England
1971 1991 President, Carnegie Endowment for International Peace
1995 Married Jane Dudley Casey Kuczynski
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Thomas Lowe Hughes (1925-) span the dates 1918-2018, with the bulk of the material dating from 1961 to 1991. The collection documents Hughes's career in United States politics and foreign policy, especially as an aide to United States politicians, Chester Bowles and Senator Hubert H. Humphrey, as director of the Department of State's Bureau of Intelligence and Research, and, later, as the president of the Carnegie Endowment for International Peace. The collection is organized into eight series: United States Congress, Department of State, Carnegie Endowment for International Peace, General Correspondence, Speeches and Writings, Boards and Associations, Personal File, and National Security Classified Information.
The collection documents Hughes's interest and work in federal politics and foreign policy, much of which was informed by his early involvement with and leadership in the Student Federalists movement as a student at Carleton College and his travels throughout Europe as a Rhodes scholar in the immediate postwar period. His papers comprehensively cover the trajectory of his career in American foreign policy, beginning in the United States Congress as an administrative assistant to Chester Bowles and as legislative counsel to Senator Hubert H. Humphrey, then moving into various leadership roles in the Department of State and, finally, the Carnegie Endowment for International Peace. Hughes's professional contacts, associations, and affiliations, many of which Hughes worked to foster and maintain for the duration of his career and beyond, feature prominently through correspondence and meeting notes, filed across several series and found throughout the collection.
The collection’s series are listed and briefly described below. A fuller description of each series and a list of its contents can be accessed in the series descriptions within the container list.
The United States Congress series contains materials documenting Hughes's early career working as legislative counsel to Senator Hubert H. Humphrey (1955-1958) and his work as an administrative assistant to Congressman Chester Bowles (1959-1960), as well as his continued professional and personal associations with both throughout his career.
The Department of State series contains material documenting Hughes's positions with the Bureau of Intelligence and Research (INR) and the United States Embassy, London.
The Carnegie Endowment for International Peace series spans the years 1948-2008, with the bulk of the material reflecting Hughes’s tenure as the organization’s president between 1971 and 1991. This series primarily contains records of major projects, events, and functions the endowment undertook under Hughes's tutelage.
The General Correspondence series was maintained as received and is arranged into three groupings: Alphabetical file, Chronological file, and Special signatures. The series primarily documents Hughes’s professional career in the Department of State and Carnegie Endowment for International Peace, with the majority reflecting Hughes’s years at the Carnegie Endowment.
The Speeches and Writings series contains transcripts of speeches Hughes gave at a variety of professional and personal engagements, articles, and an extensive collection of notes pertaining to speech and article ideas, meetings, and other professional matters.
The Boards and Associations series documents Hughes’s involvement with various international affairs think tanks and nongovernmental organizations.
The Personal File contains material related to Hughes’s education, military service, and endeavors outside of his later professional career.
The remaining series contains National Security Classified Information associated with Hughes's tenure with the Department of State and United States Congress as an aide to Hubert Humphrey and Chester Bowles.
Arrangement of the Collection
This collection is arranged in eight series:
United States Congress, 1940-2018
Department of State, 1947-2009
Carnegie Endowment for International Peace, 1948-2008
General Correspondence, 1943-2006
Speeches and Writings, 1955-2017
Boards and Associations, 1967-2013
Personal File, 1918-2017
National Security Classified Information, 1961-1970
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Annenberg, Walter H., 1908-2002.; Bowles, Chester, 1901-1986.; Bowles, Chester, 1901-1986. Ambassador's report. 1954.; Hiss, Alger.; Hughes, Alice Lowe, 1894-1967--Correspondence.; Hughes, Evan Raymond, 1892-1954--Correspondence.; Hughes, Thomas Lowe, 1925-; Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978--Correspondence.; Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978.; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963.; Mondale, Walter F., 1928-2021--Correspondence.
Organizations
Arms Control Association (Washington, D.C.); Balliol College (University of Oxford)--Students.; Carleton College (Northfield, Minn.)--Students.; Carnegie Endowment for International Peace.; Carnegie Endowment for International Peace. Face-to-Face (Program); Carnegie Endowment for International Peace. Future of Arms Control Panel.; Foundation for World Government (ʻEn ha-Shofeṭ, Israel)); Mid-Atlantic Club.; Oxford-Cambridge Association.; Student Federalists--Correspondence.; Student Federalists.; United States. Air Force.; United States. Congress.; United States. Congress. Senate. Committee on Labor and Public Welfare. Subcommittee on Labor and Labor-Management Relations.; United States. Department of State.; United States. Department of State. Bureau of Intelligence and Research.; United States. Embassy (Great Britain); Yale Law School--Students.
Subjects
Cold War.; Cuban Missile Crisis, 1962.; Defenses.; Diplomatic and consular service, American--Great Britain.; Diplomatic and consular service, American--India.; International organization.; International relations--Periodicals.; International relations.; Nuclear weapons.; Political campaigns--United States.; Presidents--United States--Election--1960.; Rhodes scholarships.; Security, International.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975.
Places
Europe, Western--Foreign relations--United States.; Europe--Description and travel.; Germany--Foreign relations--United States.; Germany--History--Unification, 1990.; Great Britain--Foreign relations--United States.; India--Description and travel.; India--Foreign relations--United States.; India--Politics and government--1947-; Pakistan--Description and travel.; South Asia.; Soviet Union--Foreign relations--United States.; United States--Foreign relations--20th century.; United States--Foreign relations--21st century.; United States--Foreign relations--Europe, Western.; United States--Foreign relations--Germany.; United States--Foreign relations--Great Britain.; United States--Foreign relations--India.; United States--Foreign relations--Soviet Union.; United States--Politics and government--20th century.; United States--Politics and government--21st century.; Vietnam.
Titles
Foreign affairs.; Foreign policy.
Occupations
Diplomats.; Public officials.
Container List
- United States Congress, 1940-2018 (Box 1-15)
  The United States Congress series contains materials documenting Hughes's early career working as legislative counsel to Senator Hubert H. Humphrey (1955-1958) and his work as an administrative assistant to Congressman Chester Bowles (1959-1960), as well as his continued professional and personal associations with both throughout his career. The series also contains a limited amount of material documenting Hughes’s association with Vice President Walter F. Mondale. The Chester Bowles material documents Hughes’s work for Bowles's congressional office and campaigns, including correspondence from constituents, drafts of books and articles Hughes edited for Bowles, files documenting bills Bowles worked on, as well as his platforms and policies. Bowles’s participation in John F. Kennedy’s 1960 presidential campaign and subsequent appointment to Kennedy’s administration as undersecretary of state is well represented through copies of letters to Kennedy. Replies from Kennedy are present to a lesser degree. Also featured is material relating to Bowles's two appointments as United States ambassador to India, including drafts of his book, Ambassador's Report, and correspondence to Hughes from his second tenure as ambassador. The Hubert H. Humphrey material documents Hughes’s work with Humphrey as well as his continued association until Humphrey’s death in 1978 and Hughes’s involvement with Humphrey’s legacy after his death. Materials cover Humphrey’s policies in the Senate, his electoral campaigns, the inner workings of his Senate office, and, to a limited degree, his vice presidency. The Walter F. Mondale material is limited and consists of correspondence between Mondale and Hughes and ephemera related to Mondale.
  Material types include correspondence, memoranda, notes, ephemera, writings, drafts, and clippings.
  Arranged alphabetically by name and then alphabetically by topic or material type.
  - Bowles, Chester (Box 1)
    - Ambassador's Report, notes and drafts, 1953-1954, (3 folders) (Box 1)
    - Amendments, 1959 (Box 1)
    - Area redevelopment bill, 1958-1962 (Box 1)
    - Bay of Pigs Invasion, Cuba, 1961 (Box 1)
    - Bills, 1959-1960, (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Bowles, Sam, 1961-1968 (Box 1)
    - Congressional Record, 1959-1960 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
      - Chronological, 1954-1975 See also Container CL 1, same heading, (3 folders) (Box 1)
      - Chronological, 1955-1985 See also Container CL 1, same heading, (7 folders) (Box 2)
      - "Important," 1953-1959 (Box 2)
      - India, 1964-1969 See also Container CL 1, same heading, (2 folders) (Box 2)
      - Kennedy, John F., 1959-1960 (Box 2)
      - To Republicans, 1959-1960 (Box 2)
    - Defense, 1960, (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - Democratic National Convention, ephemera, 1960 (Box 3)
    - Democratic Party politics, 1959-1960 (Box 3)
    - Democratic platform, 1960 (Box 3)
    - Democratic platform committee, 1960 (Box 3)
    - Diary (Hughes entries about Bowles), 1954-1960 (Box 3)
    - Election (1958), campaign for House of Representatives, 1946-1959, (3 folders) (Box 3)
    - Election (1960) (Box 4)
      - Campaign, 1960 (Box 4)
      - Campaign and convention, 1960 (Box 4)
      - Campaign dinner, 1960 (Box 4)
      - Campaign for president, 1960, (2 folders) (Box 4)
      - Campaign platform, 1960 (Box 4)
      - Campaign research, 1959-1960, (2 folders) (Box 4)
      - "Dark Horse President," 1960 (Box 4)
      - General, 1960 (Box 4)
      - Withdrawal from Connecticut congressional race, 1960 (Box 4)
    - Ephemera, 1946-1956 (Box 4)
    - Events and miscellany, 1954-1960 (Box 4)
    - Foreign Affairs Committee report, Edna Kelly, 1959-1960 (Box 5)
    - Funeral, 1986 (Box 5)
    - General, 1951-1960, (8 folders) (Box 5)
    - General, 1960-1980 See also Container CL 1, same heading, (6 folders) (Box 6)
    - House Foreign Affairs Committee, 1959-1960 (Box 6)
    - House of Representatives, office file, 1959-1960 (Box 6)
    - India, 1954-1959 (Box 6)
    - India, 1962-1967 See also Container CL 1, same heading, (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - Johnson, Lyndon B., 1964 (Box 7)
    - Kennedy, John F. (Box 7)
      - Campaign, 1960 (Box 7)
      - Politics and notes, 1960 (Box 7)
      - Sorensen, Theodore C., 1960 (Box 7)
    - Kissinger, Henry, memoranda, 1954 (Box 7)
    - Miscellany, 1954, 1960, undated (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous notes and reminiscences, circa 1990-2017 (Box 7)
    - Mutual Security Act, foreign aid, 1959 (Box 7)
    - Notes for Chester Bowles, 1954 (Box 7)
    - Obituaries, memorial service, 1986 (Box 7)
    - Office file, China, Germany, 1961 (Box 7)
    - Oral history about Bowles, Hughes transcripts, 1973-1977 (Box 7)
    - Oral history about Bowles, Hughes transcripts, 1973-1977 (Box 8)
    - Peace Corps, 1961 (Box 8)
    - Press releases, 1959-1960, (4 folders) (Box 8)
    - "Record of the Passage from Hamilton, Bermuda, to New London, Connecticut," 1940 (Box 8)
    - Résumé and diary, Hughes, 1955-1960 (Box 8)
    - Reunification of Germany, 1959 (Box 8)
    - Speeches, 1954 (Box 8)
    - U-2 (aircraft) incident, 1960, (2 folders) (Box 9)
    - Undersecretary of state (Box 9)
      - Exit from position, 1961 (Box 9)
      - Office file, 1959-1961 See also Container CL 1, same heading (Box 9)
      - Transition to position, 1960-1961, (3 folders) (Box 9)
    - Writings (Box 9)
      - Africa, 1955 (Box 9)
      - Africa, notes, 1955 (Box 9)
      - Articles, speeches, typed notes, 1952-1955 (Box 9)
      - Book, Hughes drafts, 1954 (Box 10)
      - Columns, 1959 (Box 10)
      - Drafts, articles for The Hill, 1954-1955, (2 folders) (Box 10)
      - General, 1954-1955, (3 folders) (Box 10)
      - General, 1954-1956, (3 folders) (Box 11)
    - Yale interns, 1959 (Box 11)
  - Humphrey, Hubert H. (Box 11)
    - Analysis and reminiscences by Hughes, 1999-2017 (Box 11)
    - Bills (Box 11)
      - S.964, Area Redevelopment Act, Co-Sponsor, Banking and Currency, 1955-1958, (2 folders) (Box 11)
      - S.3308, Revise Federal Election Laws to Prevent Corrupt Practices in Federal Elections, 1956 (Box 11)
    - Bills by Humphrey (Box 11)
      - 84th Congress, 1st session, 1955 (Box 11)
      - 84th Congress, 2nd session, 1956 (Box 11)
      - 85th Congress, 1st session, 1957 (Box 11)
      - 85th Congress, 2nd session, 1958 (Box 11)
    - Celebration of Humphrey, 2003 (Box 11)
    - Civil Rights Act, vote tallies, drafts, 1957 (Box 11)
    - Committee on Foreign Relations, 1957 (Box 11)
    - Diary, entries related to Humphrey (by Hughes), 1944-1960 (Box 12)
    - Draft board, Hughes Air Force commission (Humphrey's role), 1952 (Box 12)
    - Eisele, Albert (The Hill), 2003-2011 (Box 12)
    - Election campaign, Senate, 1954-1960, (3 folders) (Box 12)
    - Election materials (not Humphrey), undated (Box 12)
    - Events (Box 12)
      - General, 1956-1962 (Box 12)
      - Presidential inauguration, 1957 (Box 12)
    - General, 1944-1957, (4 folders) (Box 12)
    - General, 1957-1977, undated See also Container CL 1, same heading, (5 folders) (Box 13)
    - Holiday cards and newsletters, circa 1946-2001, undated (Box 13)
    - Howard, Frances Humphrey, 1991-2002 (Box 13)
    - Hubert H. Humphrey Institute of Public Affairs, 1978-2008, (2 folders) (Box 13)
    - Interviews about Humphrey (Box 13)
      - General, 2001-2017 (Box 13)
      - Solberg, Carl, 1981-1982 (Box 13)
    - Kampelman, Max M., writings, 1983, 1991 (Box 14)
    - Memorial service, 1978 (Box 14)
    - Miscellany, 1988-2016 (Box 14)
    - Newsletters, 1953-1954 (Box 14)
    - Notes (Box 14)
      - Conversations, 1966 (Box 14)
      - Humphrey and the Peace Corps, undated (Box 14)
      - Memoirs, 1976 (Box 14)
      - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 14)
      - On Humphrey, 1965 See also Container CL 1, same heading (Box 14)
    - Office miscellaneous, 1955-1959 (Box 14)
    - Oral history about Humphrey, 1978-1979 (Box 14)
    - Press releases, 1964, 1972-1973, (2 folders) (Box 14)
    - Senate chamber map and passes, 1951 (Box 14)
    - Senate restaurant menu, 1957 (Box 14)
    - Senate Subcommittee on Labor and Labor-Management Relations, 1950-1953 See also Container 200, Washington, D.C., correspondence, (2 folders) (Box 14)
    - Speeches, drafts, 1964 See also Container CL 1, same heading (Box 14)
    - Travel, Europe, 1958 (Box 15)
    - Tristani, Anne Howard, 2002-2015 (Box 15)
    - Vice presidency, 1966-1967 (Box 15)
    - Vietnam, memo to President Johnson (notes and draft), 1965, 2006 (Box 15)
  - Mondale, Walter F. (Box 15)
    - "Carter-Mondale on the Issues," 1976 (Box 15)
    - Correspondence, 1952, 1967-2018 (Box 15)
    - General, 1977-1984, (2 folders) (Box 15)
    - Presidential campaign, 1984 (Box 15)
    - Running Mate transcript, 1996 (Box 15)
    - Speech, Council on Foreign Relations, 1986 (Box 15)
- Department of State, 1947-2009 (Box 15-36)
  The Department of State series contains material documenting Hughes's positions with the Bureau of Intelligence and Research (INR) and the United States Embassy, London. The material ranging from 1961 to 1969 covers Hughes’s time as the deputy director, then director of INR and includes meeting notes, correspondence, briefings, and reports relating to the Cuban Missile Crisis, the Vietnam War, and other issues relating to the Cold War. Travel files document a 1963 trip Hughes took to Germany and England in conjunction with John F. Kennedy’s European tour and a 1964 trip to India and Pakistan resulting in a comprehensive debriefing on the Indian subcontinent. Files also include material on departmental politics and business, Senate hearings, and special study groups. The chronological files of George C. Denney within the series document Denney’s time as deputy director of INR (1963-1974), and cover many of the same topics. Material also includes notes and articles written and collected by Hughes after his tenure at INR that primarily reflect on INR’s role in world events. The London Embassy files document Hughes’s professional activities as minister and deputy chief of mission at the United States Embassy in London, England, from 1969 to1970. During this time, Hughes served as the second in command to Ambassador Walter H. Annenberg. These materials include correspondence, speeches, schedules and guest lists for embassy events, notes, printed matter, and clippings.
  Material types include correspondence, speeches, memoranda, notes, reports, briefings, itineraries, and clippings.
  Arranged alphabetically by topic or material type.
  - Bureau of Intelligence and Research (INR) (Box 15)
    - American Legion report on Foreign Service, 1964 (Box 15)
    - Applicants, potential, 1961-1966 (Box 15)
    - Appointment to INR, 1961 See also Container CL 1, same heading (Box 15)
    - Appointments, 1966-1969 See also Container CL 1, same heading, (2 folders) (Box 16)
    - Articles on INR, function and organization, 1967 (Box 16)
    - Austin, Anthony (Gulf of Tonkin Resolution), 1971 (Box 16)
    - Awards, 1967 (Box 16)
    - Bowles, Chester, 1962 See also Containers CL 1 and TS 1, same heading (Box 16)
    - Burks, David, 1961-1968 (Box 16)
    - China, 1959-1963, 2000-2001 (Box 16)
    - Chinese nuclear issue, 1960-1965 (Box 16)
    - Chronological file (Box 16)
      - 1961-1969 See also Container CL 1, same heading, (5 folders) (Box 16)
      - 1966-1969 See also Container CL 1, same heading, (5 folders) (Box 17)
    - Clippings (Box 17)
      - Featuring Hughes, 1961-1970 (Box 17)
      - State Department, 1962 (Box 17)
    - Cocktail party, 1968 (Box 17)
    - Cohen, Avner, "Israel and the Bomb," related notes and documents, 1967, 1998-2000 (Box 17)
    - Conferences (Box 17)
      - Airlie House, Warrenton, Va., 1967 (Box 17)
      - Council on Religion and International Affairs, Washington, D.C., 1967 (Box 17)
      - "Dupont," 1963 (Box 17)
    - Congress (1967), 1958-1968 (Box 17)
    - Congressional briefing, 1964 (Box 17)
    - Cuba notes, 1961-1965 (Box 17)
    - Cuban Missile Crisis briefing, autographs of attendees and miscellaneous, 1962, 2000 See also Container TS 1, same heading (Box 17)
    - Cuban Missile Crisis, notes, 1962 (Box 18)
    - Culebra Island, Puerto Rico, 1970 See also Container CL 1, same heading (Box 18)
    - Denney, George C., file (Box 18)
      - Africa trip, 1964 (Box 18)
      - Chronological file (Box 18)
        - 1963-1965 See also Containers CL 1 and TS 1, same heading, (7 folders) (Box 18)
        - 1965-1967 See also Containers CL 1, CL 2, and TS 1, same heading, (9 folders) (Box 19)
        - 1967-1968 See also Containers CL 1 and TS 1, same heading, (9 folders) (Box 20)
        - 1968-1973 See also Container CL 2, same heading, (10 folders) (Box 21)
        - 1973-1974 See also Container CL, 2, same heading, (2 folders) (Box 22)
    - Department of Defense research, 1965 (Box 22)
    - Desk diary, 1961-1965, (5 folders) (Box 22)
    - Employment search, 1968-1969 (Box 22)
    - Evans, Allan, trip memoranda, 1966 (Box 22)
    - Fiftieth anniversary, 1963-1967, 1997, 2004 (Box 22)
    - Flemming Award nomination, 1965 (Box 22)
    - Frankel, Charles, committee, 1967 (Box 22)
    - Fulbright, J.W., 1964 (Box 22)
    - Goheen, Robert, Education and World Affairs (EWA), 1966 (Box 22)
    - Hatch Act (1964), 1953-1960 (Box 22)
    - Haviland, H. Field, 1968 (Box 23)
    - Helms, Richard, 1969, 1994 See also Container CL 2, same heading (Box 23)
    - Heren, Louis, fiasco, 1971 (Box 23)
    - Hilsman, Roger, 1961-1975, 1990-1991 See also Container CL 2, same heading, (4 folders) (Box 23)
    - Hilsman, Roger, book excerpts, undated (Box 23)
    - Hilsman, Roger, clippings, 1964-1968 (Box 23)